דף daf עין א Ayin Aleph we caught up with עין
א
עמוד ב
Ayin Aleph Amud
Beis at the two dots. Okay, so we had introduced the final
two dots about twelve lines from the bottom. We'd introduced the idea
that very important גמרא Gemara yesterday, but what's considered the five grains
has profound halachic implications for חמץ, chametz, מצה, matzah, the prohibition of
חדש, chadash, המוציא, Hamotzi, מזונות, Mezonos, etc. We'll discuss the question specifically
of the oats, although traditionally that's always been assumed to be one
of them. Anyway, now we look on to the next part of
the משנה Mishnah that says that until the עומר Omer is brought,
you can't cut any of the grains. Again, it does not just
apply to barley. Until it's and until the עומר Omer is brought,
you can't eat the new grain. Again, any of the five grains.
The question is, when does the prohibition of cutting begin? Does the...
I mean, excuse me, when does the prohibition of cutting over? Is
it over when the עומר Omer is cut, or is it over
when the עומר Omer is brought? That is the issue of our
גמרא. Gemara. Actually, there's a debate, רש״י תוספות, Rashi Tosafot, how to
read our גמרא. Gemara. We're going to read according to תוספות. Tosafot.
So let's take a look. So the two ולקצור לפני העומר, V'liktzor
lifnei ha'Omer, it says you cannot cut the new grain before the
עומר. Omer. Again, about fifteen lines from the bottom, beginning of the
line. מנא הני מילי? Mina hanei mili? Where is this from? אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, עד ראשית ראשית מחלה. Ad Reishit Reishit
mi'Challah. Now the question is, how do we know you can't cut
grain before the עומר? Omer? That's taken for granted because it says
that the עומר Omer should be ראשית קצירכם, Reishit ktzirchem, your first
cutting, that nothing can be cut before it. It compromises the עומר's
Omer status as ראשית. reishit. The question is, how do we know
it applies to all grains and not just to barley? And from
there we have the גזירה שוה gezeira shava of ראשית ראשית reishit
reishit to חלה, Challah, and חלה Challah is called לחם, lechem, and
לחם lechem is connected to חמץ chametz and מצה, matzah, and from
there we have the whole idea of the five grains. So since
we know that it's... because of that link, we know that the
prohibition applies to all of the five grains.
The five grains, they get ripening one time?
No, actually, it's highly... it would be highly bizarre that you would
have an opportunity to cut anything other than barley. The only thing
that really is ripe at that time is the barley. But in
some chance happening, you happened to have some ripe, ripe oats or
ripe wheat, you also can't cut it. Theoretically, in practice, it really
would primarily be relevant to the barley. You're correct. Okay, מאי קודם
לעומר? Mai kodem l'Omer? Now, what's it mean that you can't cut
it before the עומר? Omer? And here the key question is, does
it mean before the bringing of the עומר Omer or before the
cutting of the עומר? Omer? Very important relevant question. You could understand
how you're going to interpret the פסוק pasuk either way. If the
עומר Omer is ראשית קצירכם, Reishit ktzirchem, does it have to have
been the only thing cut when it's brought, or does it have
to be the first thing cut when it was cut? So that
is a reasonable question.
Why would it be anything otherwise?
It should be the first thing that that anyone was cut. That
makes perfect sense.
Okay, but still, you know, when it's brought, maybe it still has
to represent this is the very first. So that's the question. Anyway,
right now we're not looking at the פסוקים. psukim. We're looking at
the text of the משנה. Mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara actually doesn't
frame it in terms of the פסוקים. psukim. Let's see what the
גמרא Gemara does with it. So it says, רבי יונה אמר... Rabbi
Yona amar... so מאי קודם לעומר? Mai kodem l'Omer? רבי יוחנן אמר
Rabbi Yochanan amar קודם קצירת העומר, Kodem kztirat ha'Omer, before the cutting
of the עומר, Omer, that if it once the עומר Omer is
cut, you can now cut the new grain. רבי יוסי ברבי זבדא
אמר Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Zavda amar קודם הבאת העומר. Kodem hava'at ha'Omer.
No, you can't bring it on... you can't cut the new grain
until you've brought the עומר. Omer.
תנן, Tnan, so we heard in a משנה, Mishnah, אסורין בחדש לפני
הפסח ולקצור לפני העומר, Asurin b'chadash lifnei ha'Pesach v'liktzor lifnei ha'Omer, that
the... all these grains are forbidden, you can't eat them, the new
grain, until פסח, Pesach, and you can't cut them before the עומר.
Omer. Now, it's very strange that it says before פסח, Pesach, because
you can't eat the new grains until actually until the second day
of פסח. Pesach. תוספות's Tosafot
גירסא girsa here is, I believe, the reverse, although one
minute.
One minute.
Okay,
so תוספות's Tosafot גירסא girsa is,
yeah, I think תוספות's Tosafot גירסא girsa is the opposite. תוספות's Tosafot
גירסא girsa is אסורין בחדש לפני העומר ולקצור לפני הפסח.
Asurin b'chadash lifnei
ha'Omer v'liktzor lifnei ha'Pesach. Okay, and the reason is like this: You
can say that it's אסורין בחדש, asurin b'chadash, you wouldn't want to
suggest that it's
מותר mutar to eat
the new grain until you brought the עומר. Omer. So it's going
to say, so then he reverses the two key words here, פסח
Pesach and עומר. Omer. It's אסורין בחדש asurin b'chadash until the עומר,
Omer, because until the עומר, Omer, obviously you're not going to eat
the new grain. But you can say you don't cut it until
פסח, Pesach, because it's safe to say you don't cut it until
פסח. Pesach. Why? Because nobody's going to say, "Oh, it's פסח, Pesach,
I can cut," because actually, if it's the first day פסח, Pesach,
you know you can't cut. Why not? יום טוב. Yom Tov. Because
it's יום טוב. Yom Tov. So therefore, we can say don't cut
it until פסח, Pesach, because then in practice, you're not going to
cut on the first day anyway. And when would be the first
opportunity you would have to cut it? מוצאי יום טוב. Motzei Yom
Tov. Then it's okay to cut it. Why is it okay to
cut it מוצאי יום טוב? Motzei Yom Tov? Because then by מוצאי
יום טוב, Motzei Yom Tov, they would have תיכף ומיד tikef u'miyad
anyway cut the עומר Omer right away. So by the time you
get a chance to go out to your field to cut right
after פסח, Pesach, the עומר Omer would have already been cut. And
we learned that that works very nicely... one minute, that works very
nicely if you're allowed to cut after the עומר Omer was cut.
It doesn't work if you're not allowed to cut until the עומר
Omer was
brought.
Right. So that is so with ביצה, Beitzah, but the basic point
is that although you can do work related
מלאכות melachos related to food on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you can
only do it, the גמרא, Gemara, from the time where the גמרא
Gemara frames it as מלישה ואילך, mi-lisha ve-eilech, like if you are
dealing with flour from the time you are actually making the dough.
Conceptually the way to understand it is you could do the type
of מלאכות melachos that are done in the home of food preparation,
but not the מלאכות melachos that are done in the field for
food preparation. Okay, so that's the basic dividing line by יום טוב.
Yom Tov. You cannot do all מלאכות. melachos. You can't go out
to your field and start harvesting grain.
But on שבת Shabbos even in the מקדש Mikdash you can do
so many...
Ah, but we're not talking about the מקדש. Mikdash. We're talking out
to the individual. You the lay person don't cut any of your
new grain until פסח. Pesach.
But
why can't you cut it on פסח? Pesach?
Oh, why can you cut the עומר Omer on פסח? Pesach? Because
it's not brought, because it's not במועדו, be-mo'ado, because the only things
you can do that override שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov
are things that are the מצווה mitzvah of the day. פסח Pesach
עומר Omer is the מצווה mitzvah of the 16th, not of the
15th.
So it doesn't override it. But we know it can't be the
15th because it's יום טוב.
Yom Tov. No, I was talking about the מקדש. Mikdash. When the
משנה Mishnah tells you in the מקדש Mikdash it's not done on
the 15th because it's not the day, the day is the 16th.
When we tell you, the lay person, don't cut any of your
grain until פסח, Pesach, so if you're not cutting until פסח, Pesach,
you're also not cutting it on פסח Pesach itself. Right, because it's
יום טוב. Yom Tov. So you're only going to know that you're
only going to be able to start cutting it מוצאי יום טוב,
Motzaei Yom Tov, and then the עומר Omer would have already been
cut. Okay, so that's what we say. So תוספות Tosafos here reverses
the גירסא girsa here, אסור בחדש
ולקצור לפני העומר, assur be-chadash ve-liktzor lifnei ha-Omer, בשלמא למאן דאמר. bi-shlama
le-man de-amar. That תוספות Tosafos again reverses the גירסא girsa here, that
you can understand why תוספות Tosafos might be more elegant, requires a
change of the text, but we're going to go with that anyway
as opposed to רש"י Rashi because it makes more sense. בשלמא למאן
דאמר קודם קצירת העומר, bi-shlama le-man de-amar kodem ketzirat ha-Omer, okay after
you say that it means that the only problem is until the
עומר Omer is cut, היינו דלא קארי להו ותני להו. haynu de-lo
ka-ari le-hu ve-tani le-hu. That's why we didn't combine it all and
say don't do anything until the עומר Omer is brought, right? Because
if the איסור issur is if you can't cut the new grain
until the עומר Omer is brought and you can't eat the new
grain until the עומר Omer is brought, why not just say it
as one sentence? Right, don't do anything until the עומר Omer is
brought. אלא למאן דאמר קודם, ella le-man de-amar kodem, again tweaking the
גירסא girsa הבאת העומר, ha-va'at ha-Omer, if you can't cut the new
grain until the עומר Omer is brought, so it's the same time
as when you can eat the new grain, וערבינהו וניתנינהו, ve-arvinhu ve-nitninehu,
tell it all as one package, אסור בחדש ולקצור לפני הבאת העומר.
assur be-chadash ve-liktzor lifnei ha-ba'at ha-Omer. Don't do anything until you bring
the עומר. Omer. So again there's a lot of changing of the
גירסא girsa here to make it work for תוספות, Tosafos, but this
is a very clean read of the גמרא Gemara once you switch
the גירסא, girsa, which is basically like this: if you can start
cutting the new grain when the עומר Omer is cut and eating
the new grain when the עומר Omer is brought, we understand why
the משנה Mishnah says two things. Don't eat the new grain until
the עומר Omer is brought, don't cut the new grain until פסח,
Pesach, until יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, because they're separate stages. But
if you can't not only not eat the new grain until the
עומר Omer is brought, but not cut the new grain until the
עומר Omer is brought, it should have all said it as one
sentence. Don't do anything until the עומר Omer is brought. Very reasonable
question. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא ella you're right. It's true.
The cutting goes by the time of cutting, not by the time
of bringing, just to make Michael happy. אלא אי אתמר אסיפא אתמר.
ella ee itmar a-seifa itmar. If there was any discussion about
whether it goes by the cutting or the bringing, it's going by
the end of the משנה. Mishnah. What's the end of the משנה?
Mishnah? The end of the משנה Mishnah says the
following: אם השרישו קודם לעומר העומר מתירן. im hishrishu kodem la-Omer ha-Omer
matiran.
If they took root before the עומר, Omer, right, this is when
the grain, what type of grain does the עומר Omer permit? Only
the grain that existed when the עומר Omer was brought. What does
it mean existed? It means that the seeds already took root. Okay,
so now we're going to ask, מאי קודם לעומר? mai kodem la-Omer?
When do you judge whether the type of grain to which the
עומר Omer relates, the grain that has taken root, taken root by
when? Taken root by the time the עומר Omer was brought? Or
taken root by the time the עומר Omer was cut? You can
understand the question, right? Since the process of the עומר Omer begins
at the cutting, we're going to get to that in a minute,
but since the process of עומר Omer begins at the cutting, maybe
it relates to any grain that has taken root only when it
was from the time that it was being cut, not from the
time it was being brought. So what's the answer?
So מאי קודם לעומר? mai kodem la-Omer? What does it mean they've
taken root before the עומר? Omer? רבי יוחנן אמר קודם הבאת העומר,
Rabbi Yochanan amar kodem ha-va'at ha-Omer, as long as they took root
before the עומר Omer was brought. רבי יוסי בר זבדא אמר קודם
קצירת העומר, Rabbi Yosei bar Zavda amar kodem ketzirat ha-Omer, before the
עומר Omer was cut. And we do not resolve it. Yeah, it's
a few hours, but it still could be a difference if you
go by whatever, however you tell whether, you know, if it was
gone by I mean we whatever the שיעור shiur is, it's right.
If the שיעור shiur is normally the גמרא Gemara says two weeks
or a month, if it's not מעת לעת me-eis le-eis then you
could say it's a moot point, but maybe it's מעת לעת, me-eis
le-eis, then it's not a moot point, let's say you planted the
night at night and not at the day. Anyway, there the גמרא
Gemara leaves it unresolved. The general assumption in all other places is...
is that we judge by the grain that has taken root by
the time the עומר Omer was brought, not the עומר Omer was
cut. So actually the resolution of this is, the way again תוספות
Tosafot reads it, is that you can cut any grain from the
moment the עומר Omer is cut, the night before, you can only
eat the new grain from the time the עומר Omer is brought,
and the עומר Omer makes permissible all grain that has taken root
at the time that it was brought, okay? And that also you
know even the seeds that have just taken root. And now we're
going to turn to this final question which is who says that
it relates to seeds that have taken root and who defines that
it's taking root that's significance? So that is the final issue we
will discuss. Okay, אמר ליה רב אלעזר לרב יאשיה amar leh Rav
Elazar l'Rav Yoshia top of ע"א ע"א, Ayin Aleph Amud Aleph, רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar said to רב יאשיה, Rav Yoshia, I should say,
דדריה didarei to רב יאשיה Rav Yoshia of his generation, there was
an elder רב יאשיה Rav Yoshia which was a תנא Tanna with
those of a previous generation, so just so you shouldn't be confused
he's saying his contemporary רב יאשיה Rav Yoshia not the one that
was his non-contemporary. Okay, so he said to him the following, and
apparently he was also a younger colleague because of the way he
spoke to him, he says, and I mean not in a bad
way but in a way that you would speak to a younger
colleague, לא תיתיב אכרעא, lo taysiv akara, that comes from don't sit
on your legs meaning don't sit down עד דמפרשת לי להא מתניתין
ad demafareshas lay lehaya masnisin
until you can explain to me this following משנה Mishnah and I
don't want you to go anywhere until you explain this משנה Mishnah
to me. What's the משנה? Mishnah? מניין לעומר שמתיר בהשרשה. menayin laOmer
she-matir b'hashrashah.
So where do we know that the עומר Omer meaning our משנה
Mishnah says it goes by the time it takes root? How do
we know that the עומר, Omer, you know, makes things that have
taken root it makes them permissible? Maybe it only makes permissible the
grain that's fully standing and maybe if grain grew later you'd have
to wait a full year until the next עומר? Omer? Right, how
do we know that it relates to grain that has, you know,
even that's now taken root?
So, מנלן, menalan, where do you know it from? דכתיב אביב. de-ksiv
Aviv. It says that the עומר Omer is אביב. Aviv. It is
the, you know, it is fresh. So the fact that it says
אביב, Aviv, that this is now sort of, not fresh, what's the
word, but now ripened, thank you, it's now
ripened, so לאו מכלל דאיכא דלאו אביב, lav mikhlal d'ika d'lav Aviv,
so it's telling you make sure to bring the עומר Omer that
it's ripened grain, it suggests that there's other grain out there in
the field that's not yet ripe. So therefore the, and the עומר
Omer presumably relates to them because it's in reference to them, so
the עומר Omer works on the not yet ripe grain. So you
see the grain doesn't have to be ripe. But then he says
wait, the
עומר Omer is brought from ripe grain to permit ripened and unripened.
First of all that can't be true anyway, if you think for
a minute, you need the עומר Omer to allow not only the
barley but also the wheat. The wheat isn't going to really be
ripe. I mean the גמרא Gemara interestingly doesn't say that, but the
wheat isn't going to be ripe for another seven weeks. So obviously
it has to relate to grain that's not yet ripe.
Because not only relate to say ולחם מתיר v'lechem matir from the
מקדש, Mikdash, right? And the עומר's Omer מתיר, matir, exactly, exactly.
So it obviously has to work on not only the barley that
might be ripe but it has to work on the wheat.
But that's sort of reading your assumptions into the פסוק. pasuk. He's
trying to prove it from the פסוק. pasuk.
So I understand, but you know, fine, but anyway that's not what
the גמרא Gemara says, but I'm just telling you intuitively clearly we
understand that it's not limited to ripe grain. Okay, so the fact
that it says אביב Aviv means that there's other grain out there
that isn't ripe and the עומר Omer still working for them.
So the גמרא Gemara says fine, דלאו אביב, de-lav Aviv, I'll accept
that there's other grain that's not ripe, ולעולם דאייתי שליש, u-le'olam d'atyei
shelish, maybe at least it's a third ripened. A third ripened is
a critical stage for the גמרא Gemara which makes it considered at
least to be a פרי, peri, at least to be considered like
edible and have a certain status of, you know, a grain and
so on. So therefore maybe it doesn't have to be ripe, but
maybe it has to be at least a certain degree of maturity,
at least a third ripe and not just a little feeling, right,
not exactly not a little seed in the ground with roots. אלא
אמר שמואל, ela amar Shmuel, rather שמואל Shmuel said like this, here's
what it is and here you see why we're going, this is
pointing us to the cutting of the עומר Omer not the bringing,
מהחל חרמש בקמה תחל לספור, me-hachel chermesh ba-kamah tachel lispor, right? From
the time the sickle hits the standing grain you count starting your
seven weeks. So that means what? לאו מכלל דאיכא דלאו בר חרמש.
lav mikhlal d'ika d'lav bar chermesh. The fact that it again says
that your עומר Omer is coming because of the sickle is cutting
down the grain means that there's some other grain out there that's
not yet ready for the sickle and you're only bringing your עומר
Omer from the stuff obviously that's ready for the sickle. I understand
that's the way the גמרא Gemara is reading it. Michael, I'm not
going to prove it to you beyond what the גמרא Gemara says.
Okay, so there you see that there's other standing grain out there
that's not ready for the sickle and therefore the עומר Omer relates
to them. So the גמרא Gemara says fine, but that still doesn't
get you to the seedling. So the גמרא Gemara says דלאו בר
חרמש, de-lav bar chermesh, maybe it's not ready for the sickle, ולעולם
שחת, u-le'olam shachas, it's still like fodder, meaning there's stuff that, you
know, the stalks are there, the whatever the top is called, what's
the top called, whatever, anyway the top with the grains, you know,
the grain isn't ripened, but the stalks are there, so it's fit
for fodder. It's not fit for harvesting because there's no grain yet.
Okay, but maybe at least you've got the stalks. It doesn't prove
the little seedling in the ground. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רבי יצחק קמה, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak kama, so רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak
the elder, the first one said, no קמה, kama, I can't believe
I just said that, אמר רבי יצחק קמה, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak kama,
לאו מכלל דלאו בר קמה. lav mikhlal d'lav bar kama. that the
sickle is hitting the standing grain. So the standing grain means that
there exists grain that's not even standing grain yet. Again because it's
saying that the עומר Omer is this, it means there's other stuff
out there that it relates to that's not yet at this stage.
So if the עומר Omer is standing, that means there's other stuff
that has not even yet grown their stalks, isn't yet even fodder.
And therefore the עומר Omer relates to them as well. Now we're
getting closer because there's no stalks, maybe it's still, maybe it really
is the seedling.
So the גמרא Gemara says, I'm still not ready to admit. The
לאו בר קמה, Lav bar kama, I'll admit that it's not yet
standing grain, but ולעולם אגם, veleolam agam, but maybe it's sort of
like an אגם agam is a swamp, meaning maybe it's still little
little shootlings that are coming out of the ground. You still don't
know, is that a word? Shootling? Anyway, you still don't know that
it's a seed with just with roots. Maybe something has still risen
from the ground. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, so רבא Rava אלא אמר רבא, ela Amar Rava, so rather
רבא Rava says אשר תזרע. Asher tizrah. Now this is, this is
not by the עומר, Omer, this is by, this is by בכורים,
Bikkurim, this is by שבועות. Shavuos. It says וחג הקציר בכורי מעשיך
אשר תזרע בשדה, Vechag hakatzir bikkurei maasecha asher tizra basadeh,
the holiday of harvesting, the first of your fruits that you will
plant in the field. So because it says the first of your
fruits that you will plant, so it's referring to, it's going back,
this is the way the גמרא's Gemara's reading it, to the fruits
that came from, you know, that were sort of went through the
עומר. Omer. Again, as the גמרא's Gemara's understanding is that the only
thing that the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem works on is stuff that
already passed through the התיר heter of the עומר. Omer. So therefore,
if the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem is working on something that is
now being referred to as אשר תזרע, Asher tizrah, which is planted,
it means that the עומר Omer was מתיר matir it even when
it was at the stage yet of just אשר תזרע Asher tizrah
that
had just been, that had just been passed,
something that had just been planted. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
משעת זריעה. mishat zriah. So you see you bring the שתי הלחם
Shtei Halechem from something that was planted, it's called something that was
planted. And it means planted at the stage of the עומר Omer
because the עומר Omer is a stage of making it fit now
for the שתי הלחם. Shtei Halechem. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
ליה רב פפא לרבא, Amar lei Rav Pappa le-Rava, יהי הכי אף
על גב דלא השריש נמי, yehi hachi af al gav delo hishrish
nami, so even if it didn't take root, if it was just
put in the
ground? אמר ליה, Amar lei, סודני, Sudani, so סודני Sudani here is
a like a like a it seems to be a term of
endearment. רש"י Rashi says it's a word that means like a תלמיד
חכם. talmid chacham. It also could mean that רב פפא Rav Pappa
was a beer maker, and
סודני Sudani might have been the name of the profession of
the brewer,
either a praise or a put-down.
Oh, I don't know if a put-down, well maybe you're right, put-down
you're a beer maker, you beer maker.
Okay, right that's okay, so that's a good point. So either hey
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham or hey beer maker, בשדה כתיב, basadeh ksiv,
it says אשר תזרע בשדה. Asher tizra basadeh. It has to be
in the ground, not just like placed there, but to be in
becomes part of the ground, so it has to take root in
order to be considered part of the ground. So that's how we
know again, you know, Michael and and maybe are skeptical of this,
always the question is, is did they just have this מסורת, masoret,
but this was really a דרשה, drasha, so the גמרא Gemara seems
to take the דרשה drasha seriously and as I've pointed out, you
have to say this because if you don't say this, then you're
gonna have the all of the wheat and all the stuff that's
growing afterwards, the later crops, are not going to be permissible. So
obviously it's got to relate to stuff that is not yet ready
for harvesting. Okay. So that's how we know that the עומר Omer
does מתיר matir all of that. And as we also said, the
cutting of the עומר Omer is what's מתיר matir you to begin
to cut the new grain. And now we continue with the focus
on the cutting of the עומר Omer and talk about places where
they might have been able to cut prior to the cutting of
the עומר. Omer. If you will remember this came up in the
past because we said after the עומר Omer was brought, all of
a sudden all the shopkeepers started taking out all of their roasted
grain. Well where'd they get the grain? Because they cut it. Well
where'd they cut it? So again, what we've now found out is
they could have cut it last night after the עומר Omer was
cut, but again if you're doing a large-scale operation and you want
to have a lot of grain available for everybody first thing after
the עומר Omer is brought, you don't want to you're not going
to limit yourself to the night before. So the גמרא Gemara said
there actually might be some places which you are allowed to cut
before the עומר Omer was cut and that's what this משנה Mishna
turns to, places that you can't bring the עומר Omer from. And
that's what this משנה Mishna talks about, so let's take a look.
Wasn't there a משנה Mishna before?
No, the משנה Mishna before related to this point. Okay. קוצרים בית
השלחים שבעמקים. Kotzrin beis hashalchin she-ba’amakim. You can cut irrigated fields in
the valley. אבל לא גודשים, Aval lo godshim, but you cannot, you
know, make them into into sheaves. We'll let you do it, but
we don't want, you know, we still want to be sensitive to
the, you know, to the fact that it's impinging on the עומר,
Omer, so we don't want to make it a full-scale operation. So
we'll allow you to cut it, but we will not allow we
do not want you to make it into sheaves. אנשי יריחו, Anshei
Yericho, the people in יריחו, Yericho, קוצרים ברצון חכמים. kotzrin b’ratzon chachamim.
They cut in the with the approval of the sages. Apparently they
had these irrigated fields in the valley. And the other point that's
made up, there's two issues here. No, anywhere in ישראל, Yisrael, anywhere
in ישראל Yisrael you can bring the עומר Omer from. No, anywhere
in ישראל. Yisrael. Yeah, but that's never used as an exception. Okay,
in theory since it could be brought from there. So anyway,
there are two factors that are always going on here. On the
one hand... On the one hand you have to explain why it's
technically allowed, on the other hand you have to explain why we
practically want to allow it because it's just a bad idea to
have a lot of people start cutting things before the עומר, Omer,
other people that aren't in places where it's not allowed, they'll start
doing it too. So a factor of all these cases of when
it would be allowed was also that there was a הפסד hefsed
that these types of things were at risk if they were not
cut of loss if they were not cut earlier.
And could that and earlier?
Well maybe really it should have been cut a week earlier, maybe
they didn't cut it the day before the עומר, Omer, they cut
it two weeks before the עומר. Omer. So and that actually it
makes sense because if these things are also irrigated fields, they probably
run on some different type of a cycle than things that are
going by natural rain. So the assumption was two things. Number one
is that because you could not bring the עומר Omer from these
places, we'll discuss why in a minute but we've already said that.
In A technically it's allowed and because it was a concern of
loss, then we would actually go ahead and just let them do
it. So that was the case of אנשי יריחו. Anshei Yericho. They
would cut, they apparently they had these irrigated fields and they would
cut it, and it was with the approval of the rabbis. However,
וגודשים שלא ברצון חכמים. vegocheim shelo biratzon chachamim. They actually made it
into sheaves against the rabbis, which was with the rabbis' disapproval because
the rabbis as we said before don't want you making it into
sheaves, we don't want it to become a major operation. And nevertheless
ולא מיחו בידם, velo miku beyadam, just because they disapproved does not
mean that they made a protest and they would try to go
ahead and they tried to stop it. Sometimes there are things that
happen that you're not happy with, but it's better to tolerate it
rather than to try to make a big fuss of. So the
rabbis didn't approve but they did not try to put a stop
to it. Okay, now why are you allowed to cut in the
cases of עמקים? amakim? Why can't you bring the עומר Omer from
there? So as we said before, תוספות Tosafot says and רש״י Rashi
says or whatever
that it was not the same type of a quality grain. And
therefore there's an assumption that at least לכתחילה lechatchila you don't bring
the עומר Omer from there because it's not quality grain. And since
לכתחילה lechatchila you don't bring it from there, interestingly even if בדיעבד
bedieved it does work, that would be enough to allow you to
cut. Since it's not the place where ideally you bring the עומר
Omer from. The other possibility which מרדכי Mordechai said the other day
and which I've been thinking as well, I haven't had a chance
to check, is that maybe if it's an irrigated field and it's
not sort of as seasonal as the others, maybe it's not as
maybe maybe for reasons of non-seasonality that it can't be the עומר.
Omer. The whole point of the עומר Omer is that it's something
that is sort of seasonal and tied to the rains and tied
to the
seasons, and therefore again, it would be interesting to have a פסוק
pasuk that you could maybe tie to the
אביב, Aviv, something which connects it to the seasons. But anyway the
גמרא Gemara doesn't really explicate that. But for whatever reason you can't
do it either לכתחילה lechatchila or בדיעבד, bedieved, can't bring the עומר
Omer and therefore you're allowed to cut. יריחו Yericho in the valley?
What? יריחו Yericho in the valley?
I don't know, יריחו Yericho certainly עיר התמרים. ir hatemarim. Did it
have valleys in it? The question is here is the qualifier בעמקים
beamakim critical? The תוספות Tosafot points out and other ראשונים Rishonim point
out that earlier when the גמרא Gemara spoke about קוצרים בית השלחין,
kotzin beis hashalchin, it dropped the word בעמקים. beamakim. So there's a
question in the ראשונים Rishonim whether the qualifier of valley is significant
or whether it has to be?
What? בקעת הירדן. Bik'at Hayarden. Okay. Okay.
All right. Okay.
Now, קוצר לשחת. kotzer leshachas. Now we're going to have other types
of cuttings that are permissible before the עומר. Omer. So one is
from these types of fields. Now we're going to talk about fields
that you could bring the עומר Omer from but the way it's
being cut makes it a non-problematic harvesting before the עומר. Omer. So
let's take a look. קוצר לשחת ומאכיל לבהמה. kotzer leshachas umaachil livheima.
You can harvest for fodder and feed your animals. The type of
a harvesting that's defined as harvesting is a harvesting for human consumption.
A harvesting for שחת, shachas, right, okay, right, בקעת הירדן. Bik'at Hayarden.
A harvesting for שחת shachas is not considered a harvesting and is
therefore not prohibited. אמר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda, so says רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, אימתי, eimasai, when is that true? בזמן שמתחיל עד
שלא הביא שליש. bezman shematchil ad shelo hevi shlish. If you began
the harvesting for the fodder when the again there's that critical point,
when the grain had not yet reached the third ripened. Because then
it's not even fit for human consumption. It's only fit for animal
consumption. And therefore that defines presumably even then if you continue after
it ripens further, since you began when it was not yet fit
for human consumption, it defines the whole harvesting here as not real
harvesting. It's just creating animal fodder. Because it began at a time
when the stuff was not fit for human consumption.
שחת, shachas, animal fodder fodder. Exactly. Because they call it that because
it's basically considered waste?
No, I don't know the etymology but שחת shachas means fodder. Okay,
וקוצרים מפני. vekotzrim mipnei. Okay, so that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says. רבי שמעון אומר יקצור ויאכיל אף משהביא שליש. Rabbi Shimon omer,
yiktzor veyaachil af mishehevi shlish. Not a problem. It's all about your
intention. It doesn't matter, even if the grain is a third ripened
and in theory is fit for human consumption, if your intention is
to cut it for fodder, that's fine, that's not a problem. So
everybody agrees that a harvesting that is not a sort of harvesting
for food is okay, the debate is what's considered a do you
need it just to be in your mind that it's not food
for your
consumption, human food, is it
just your intention? which means at least the process began before the
wheat was third ripened grain I think you'd say.
Let me ask you this question. Let's say I want to like,
you know, harvest it quote-unquote for my animals and I'm really doing
it for myself, I'm gonna get my animals a little bit.
Right, so there's always that דקדוקי עניות dikdukei aniyut probably possibly, but
the משנה's Mishnah concerned about tricking. Look at the end of the
day, you know, so as with a lot of a lot of
Judaism, you know, there's an honor system going on here. Okay. We're
not sending out the police. All right. Now, okay. Now, so that's
one issue, that it's not harvesting for food. Now, הקוצץ מפני נטיעות,
HaKotzetz mipnei netiot, now there's another series of harvestings which are done
not for the sake for the sake of a מצוה. mitzvah. One
is מפני נטיעות mipnei netiot because of plantings. One thing רש״י Rashi
says it might mean is that it's in it's together with where
there are where there are tree saplings and there's a concern that
it will be a הפסד hefsed that it will destroy them. Of
course the or one will destroy the other. I'm telling you. Okay,
so one is a concern of הפסד. hefsed. The problem then is
yes wonderful there's a הפסד, hefsed, why is it permissible? So רש״י
Rashi also says well because maybe the harvesting we have another thing
is that you can't bring the עומר Omer from where there's a,
you know, from where there's a from a tree field. So again
it would be that exemption. But the other explanation, you don't understand?
No. There's grain growing amongst trees. You can cut it because if
you don't cut it, the roots and the trees or whatever will
destroy the grain and it's not a prohibition because you can't bring
the עומר Omer from places from כלאים. kilayim. That's the second thing
I'm going to say. So the first thing רש״י Rashi says is
it's sort of similar to the בית השלחים, Beis HaShalachin, but the
next thing רש״י Rashi says which he likes better because it fits
in the theme of the next list is that it's a כלאים
kilayim concern. That you had some grain growing, somebody else came and
planted trees or you didn't realize that and these trees are growing
up, there was an acorn, you know, that had been in the
ground you didn't know about and then a tree started growing up
and now you have a כלאים kilayim concern. So therefore you can
cut it to get out of כלאים. kilayim. And that the harvesting
of a מצוה, mitzvah, and a harvesting of a מצוה mitzvah is
permissible, that's the reading that רש״י Rashi preferred. Okay, so הקוצץ מפני
נטיעות HaKotzetz mipnei netiot and here are other מצוה mitzvah reasons you're
cutting. מפני בית האבל, mipnei beis haavel, there's you want to use
this space for the mourners to sit after they bury. They would
go out into like a courtyard and they'd sit and they'd have
a type of ניחום אבלים nichum avelim right after the burial and
this is let's say near some cemetery and it's important to clear
this space. So you want to clear this space, that's a קצירה
ketzirah again for the sake of a מצוה. mitzvah. ומפני ביטול בית
המדרש, u'mipnei bitul beis hamidrash, let's say you need the space for
a ישיבה. yeshiva. Okay? They would have to they would have outdoor
study houses, you know, the sort of Greek model, you know, you'd
have these, you know, you'd have people would be sitting outdoors and
they needed more space for more students. So if you want to
open a wink wink thing, it seems to me. I don't think
so. The point is if you're if you have these large wheat
fields, right, sometimes if you need a certain usable space, the best
way to make a usable space is you cut a patch off
down of a wheat field and now you've got a nice space
to sit.
What if they say like let's say there's a wheat field on
the left and there's nothing on the right, can I say oh
I want to sit on the right because it's sunnier to...
No, that no, no, I don't know
what you're saying at all.
What these situations you have to judge the common...
Right. Now, your question is can't people now game the system? Maybe
yes. But where at least in the משנה Mishnah I don't read
it the way you're reading. I think these are a serious need.
If you're in a place right now you, right, I mean, you
know, if what we would say is if you need a space,
well there's maybe find a deserted lot somewhere. If you're in an
agricultural society and they've these huge wheat fields, why not just cut
a little patch of the wheat down and you have a nice
little space to sit. But they can't mow the whole field. No,
no, no, not mow the whole field. You mow the space that
you need for this thing. Okay. So... Yeah, this
guy. Sorry. Alright. So, לא יעשם כריכות. lo yaasum kerichot. Now similar
to before where we said don't make it into sheaves, here we
say if you're going to cut for these purposes, don't make it
into bundles. I don't know the difference exactly between bundles and sheaves,
I knew you'd ask. But I don't know. אבל מניחים צבטים, aval
menichim tzvatim, but you can leave them sort of like, you know,
in like little piles without actually making them into bundles. By the
way, I put up on the website a whole little section from
from Yehuda Feliks's book on agriculture in Talmudic times where he discusses
the process of harvesting and has a subsection specifically about how they
cut the עומר. Omer. So, you might want to look at that.
Okay. What so anyway, מצות העומר לבוא מן הקמה. mitzvat haomer lavo
min hakama. The מצוה mitzvah is to come from the standing grain,
meaning cutting the grain specifically for the sake of the עומר. Omer.
לא מצא, lo matza, if there was no standing grain that was
available to bring, either it wasn't ripe or whatever, יביא מן העמרים.
yavi min ha'amarim. Now somebody of course just violated because somebody cut
the grain before the עומר Omer was cut, but somehow if that
nevertheless exists and there is pre-cut grain and even if it wasn't
done for the sake of the עומר, Omer, you can bring the
עומר Omer from grain that was already cut even though it was
cut for other purposes, from the sheaves. מצותו לבוא מן הלח. mitzvato
lavo min halach. You're supposed to bring it from fresh grain because
it says כרמל karmel and one of the things we learned from
כרמל karmel is is רך, rach, that has to be soft and
fresh. לא מצא, lo matza, if you do not find fresh grain,
יביא מן היבש. yavi min hayavesh. You can bring from dry grain.
However, it has to be this year's grain, it can't be last...
your screen. Okay, but if somehow the grain is somebody did cut
earlier and you have and it's dried, בדיעבד bedi'avad that's okay.
מצותה לקצור בלילה. Mitzvaso liktzor balayla. The מצוה mitzvah is to cut
it at night because of what I said before about תמימות, temimot,
so the תמימות temimot means you begin at night. נקצר ביום כשר.
Niktza bayom kasher. בדיעבד bedi'avad if you cut it in the day
it's כשר. kasher. And finally, דוחה את השבת. dochet hashabbat. Because it
has to be brought today on the 16th, it overrides שבת, Shabbat,
and if the 16th is שבת Shabbat you can cut it on
שבת. Shabbat. Even though in theory you could have cut it before
and had it ready, but since they understand that the מצוה mitzvah
is, the מצוה mitzvah is to cut it the day that it's
brought, so even though in theory you could do otherwise, that's the
nature of קרבנות. korbanot. That things that are the מצוה mitzvah of
the day you do today and you don't say well in theory
I could do
it otherwise, didn't happen right? Because of לא בד"ו פסח. lo badu
pesach.
Well with our calendar it wouldn't happen. Right, from the times of
the מקדש. mikdash. No, but this was actually what happens if it
was on שבת. Shabbat. Right, so but in their פסח pesach it
was על פי הראיה.
al pi hare'iya.
מחר השבת machar hashabat means מחר יום טוב. machar yom tov. So
יום טוב yom tov and שבת. shabbas. יום טוב yom tov was
on Friday. Okay, but then Michael says our time that doesn't fall
on Friday.
Right. Okay, alright, so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. תניא, Tanya, רבי בנימין אומר. Rabbi Benjamin omer. Okay, so
now we're going to first address ourselves to the idea that there
are places that it can you can cut, you can harvest grain
from, even prior to the cutting of the עומר, Omer, the harvesting
of the עומר. Omer. תניא, Tanya, רבי בנימין אומר: Rabbi Benjamin omer:
כתוב אחד אומר, kasuv echad omer, one פסוק pasuk says וקצרתם את
קצירה, ukztzartem es ketzira, you shall cut its cutting, והבאתם את עומר,
v'avaisem es omer, and bring the עומר. Omer. וכתיב, V'kasiv, another פסוק
pasuk says ראשית קצירכם, reishit ketzirchem, the first of your... in the
same פסוק. pasuk. So
it's bothered because it says you shall cut the cutting, וקצרתם את
קצירה, ukztzartem es ketzira, it's not described as ראשית, reishit, and maybe
it suggests other things are being cut as well, and this is
just one of the cuttings. So it sounds like it's not the
only thing being cut. And the other פסוק pasuk says it has
to be the ראשית. reishit. So הא כיצד, ha keitzad, how do
you reconcile it? ממקום שאתה מביא אי אתה קוצר. Mimakom she'ata meivi
ee ata kotzer. From a place where you could bring from, you
cannot cut because then obviously it would impinge on the status of
the first cutting. The ראשית. reishit. ממקום שאי אתה מביא אתה קוצר,
Mimakom she'ee ata meivi ata kotzer, if you couldn't even ever brought
from this field, אתה קוצר, ata kotzer, then you can cut, and
that maybe does not impinge as much on the status of ראשית.
reishit. One big modifier? What? You just say except the cutting is
the ראשית קצירכם. reishit ketzirchem. Does he understand the other reason to...
I mean you know whatever getting whether it's a מסורה masorah or
whatever, but that's you know Michael as with almost all of these
things you come with certain assumptions to the פסוקים. psukim. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says... now the גמרא Gemara does ask that there's
another possible read even reading it as this tension. אימא ממין שאתה
מביא אי אתה קוצר ממין שאי אתה מביא אתה קוצר? Eima mimin
she'ata meivi ee ata kotzer, mimin she'ee ata meivi ata kotzer? Maybe
it has nothing to do with the field, maybe it has to
do with the species of grain. Maybe you're allowed... you cannot cut
any barley but you can cut wheat or oats or rye, okay,
which makes a lot of sense, right? Maybe it should be the
first harvesting of the barley, but maybe the other things does not
impinge on its status of ראשית reishit and it goes about the
species
and not about the field. So the גמרא Gemara says no. ההוא
לא מצית אמרת לרבי יוחנן. Hahu lo matzi amrit l'Rabbi Yochanan. That
you can't say from רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Because רבי יוחנן's Rabbi
Yochanan דרשה drasha yesterday which just explained the משנה Mishna that learned
out from the idea that the עומר Omer is מתיר matir all
of the five grains. And since the עומר Omer is מתיר matir
all of the five grains, both whether in eating or in harvesting,
so clearly the prohibition to harvest applies to the other grains as
well. So based on the דרשה drasha of yesterday we know that
the prohibition of harvesting is not limited to barley, we know it
applies to the five grains, and therefore this permission must be based
on the field and not on the type of grain. You're looking
for the דרשה drasha of רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? Michael says the
דרשה drasha of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is where was it? ולקצור
לפני העומר. V'liktzor lifnei ha'omer. ראשית ראשית מחלה. Reishit reishit mechalla. It
says ראשית קצירכם reishit ketzirchem and by חלה challah it's called ראשית
reishit and the חלה challah of ראשית reishit we said based on
לחם lechem and מצה matza and so on is five grains. So
ראשית קצירכם reishit ketzirchem it means ראשית reishit of anything that is
like חלה, challah, any of the five grains. Okay. So that's how
we know that you can harvest in these irrigated fields. Again, quite
interestingly does not tell us why you can't bring the עומר Omer
from the irrigated fields, that is somehow self-evident. Okay,
אנשי יריחו קוצרים ברצון חכמים וגודשים שלא ברצון חכמים. anshei Yericho kotzim
bertzon chachamim v'godshin shelo bertzon chachamim. The people of יריחו Yericho would
harvest with the approval of the חכמים chachamim because they fell in
this category of בית השלחין, beit hashlachin, and but they would bundle
it not with the approval of the sages. מאן תנא דאמר מיחו
ולא מיחו. Man tanna d'amar michu v'lo michu. Now the גמרא Gemara
is saying but the end of it says the rabbis did not
protest. So who is the תנא tanna that talks about the idea
of protesting because we'll see in a minute that we have some
תנאים tannaim that talk in another... in another tongue. well in this
context but whatever in פסחים Pesachim about this idea of protesting. Who
are those- who is that תנא? Tanna? רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. It's
רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. וסבר Vesavar רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda did רבי
יהודה Rebbe Yehuda really hold that שירה דאנשי יריחו ברצון חכמים הוה
Shira De'Anshei Yericho Bertzon Chachamim Hava that the harvesting of the people
of יריחו Yericho was done with the approval of the חכמים? Chachamim?
והתניא Vehatanya here's the ברייתא. Braisa. So if that wasn't clear let's
see the ברייתא Braisa and then the question will become clear. Here's
the ברייתא, Braisa, okay? It's mentioned in פסחים Pesachim about when it
mentions about things people did with and without the sages' approval. Okay,
you might remember the famous thing about like חזקיה, Chizkiyahu, you know,
and whether he did, he was גונז Gonaze the ספר רפואות, Sefer
Refuos, he drags the bones of of his father. So there's like
a listing of things that people did with some with the חכמים's
Chachamim approval and some without the חכמים's Chachamim approval. So let's take
a look. ששה דברים עשו אנשי יריחו. Shisha Devarim Asu Anshei Yericho.
The people of יריחו Yericho did six things, you know, six sort
of unusual things.
שלשה ברצון חכמים Shelosha Bertzon Chachamim three were with the approval of
the sages and שלשה שלא ברצון חכמים Veshelosha Shelo Bertzon Chachamim three
without the approval of the sages. ואלו שברצון חכמים Ve'elu Sheberzon Chachamim
the following was with the approval of the sages:
מרכיבין דקלים כל היום Markivin Dekalin Kol Hayom they would the day
of ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, this is why it's in פסחים, Pesachim,
you're not allowed supposed to do עבודה, Avodah, you know, מלאכה Melacha
the day of ערב פסח Erev Pesach certainly from חצות Chatzos onwards
because you're supposed to be getting focusing on bringing your קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach. However, they would graft
palm trees, you know, עיר התמרים, Ir Hatemarim, they would graft palm
trees all the whole day of ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. Why? Presumably
for a combination of number one it was not considered to be
a big effort, I mean with certain type they're talking about a
certain type of grafting that was relatively simple. And number two because
it was considered to be a serious הפסד. Hefsed. Okay and again
if you're עיר התמרים, Ir Hatemarim, you know, so you gotta be
doing it right right up to יום טוב. Yom Tov. So that
that the חכמים Chachamim allowed, yes because of concerns of הפסד Hefsed
they allowed. That was ברצון
חכמים. Bertzon Chachamim. כורכין את שמע Korchin Es Shema they would wrap
the שמע. Shema. There's a question of what that means but somehow
it means that there was they did not pause they didn't sort
of make pauses in the שמע. Shema. Some say it means that
after they said השם אחד Hashem Echad they didn't pause they just
went into ברוך שם Baruch Shem without pausing between the אחד Echad
and the ברוך שם Baruch Shem or they maybe, you know, connected
certain words together without pausing between words. Now that's a little bit
strange what that means ברצון חכמים. Bertzon Chachamim. I mean maybe it
means that like, you know, is that a good thing? So maybe
it mean I there's not never really an indication that it was
necessarily good, but it wasn't bad enough to say we don't approve
of it, you know? So it was alright, you know, it's not
great but we're not going to say we don't approve of it.
וקוצרין לפני העומר Vekotzrin Lifnei Ha'omer and here is our משנה Mishna
and they would harvest before the עומר Omer because of the reasons
of הפסד Hefsed and it was a praised presumably a בית השלחין
Beis Hashalchin so the an irrigated field. That they would do ברצון
חכמים. Bertzon Chachamim. That was done with the approval of the sages.
ואלו שלא ברצון חכמים Ve'elu Shelo Bertzon Chachamim the following is without
the approval of the sages: גודשין לפני העומר Godshin Lifnei Ha'omer they
would bundle it, which you're not supposed to do before the עומר.
Omer. ומתירין גמזיות של הקדש Umatirin Gamziyos Shel Hekdesh של חרוב ושל
שקמה. Shel Charuv Veshel Shikma. Apparently they're they had an inheritance the
people of יריחו Yericho from earlier generations that they had that had
sanctified these other trees not what we're going right I'll tell you
in a minute not their palm trees but חרוב Charuv and שקמה
Shikma is I don't know שקמה Shikma is I think what sycamore
and חרוב Charuv is some other part- what what? חרוב Charuv is
carob tree? Okay anyway so these trees were had been sanctified as
הקדש Hekdesh and then the question is then they grew obviously after
they had been sanctified. That's the גמזיות. Gamziyos. גמזיות Gamziyos are like
somehow refer to continued growth afterwards, other sprouts and some that came
afterwards. So they said oh this grew afterwards because you know yeah
it's not הקדש. Hekdesh. It's it's you know it's גידולי הקדש Gidulei
Hekdesh but it's not הקדש Hekdesh and they would just go ahead
and they would use it for their own purposes and the sage
says no sorry stuff that grows from הקדש Hekdesh is also הקדש
Hekdesh and it's owned by the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay so
that's the גמזיות של הקדש. Gamziyos Shel Hekdesh. ופורצין פרצות בגגותיהם ובפרדסיהם
להאכיל נשר לעניים בשני בצורת. Uportzin Pertzos Begagoteinu Ubifardeseihen Le'achil Nesher La'aniyim
Bishne Batzores. בשבתות ובימים טובים Beshabasos Ubeyamim Tovim that's a long sentence.
So what they would do is they would make holes in their
roof and in the apparently they had like, you know, certain orchards
which were roofed over and they were holes in the roof gardens
like today. Right? And what would that allow? That would allow the
following: that the fruit that fell off of their trees again I
guess it's like mostly dates they have you know עיר התמרים Ir
Hatemarim anyway it would fall and it would somehow get collected and
fall into a place where then the poor could come and eat
from it on שבת. Shabbos. Okay כדי להאכיל לעניים Kedei Le'achil La'aniyim
נשר לעניים Nesher La'aniyim נשר Nesher stuff that naturally falls בשני בצורת
Bishne Batzores at times of a famine. So a famine everybody nobody
had food but you know if this stuff falls on שבת Shabbos
it's going to get trampled and go to waste and particularly food
is precious. So they basically did it so it would fall on
the roof maybe rolling to, you know, a hole come down into
a located place and let the poor come and feed from it
which is a great טובה. Tova. Which the problem is is that
it's on שבת Shabbos and the stuff fell off the trees on
שבת Shabbos and there is a concern number one of מוקצה Muktzah
number two that if you eat stuff that falls off a tree
on שבת Shabbos you're going to come to pick it from the
tree on שבת. Shabbos. So while their intentions were very good the
the sages did not approve of it.
They did the פורצין פרצות Portzin Pertzos on שבת? Shabbos?
No they did the פורצין פרצות Portzin Pertzos before שבת Shabbos to
and. allow the עניים aniyim to come and eat from the fruit
on שבת. Shabbos. The fruit that naturally fell and then they would
be allowed to come and eat for on שבת. Shabbos. And they
still didn't like that, you know, although you think it's a big
טובה tova or whatever, the חכמים chachamim were still concerned about eating
fruit that fell off a tree. You know, they probably would have
said that's all very lovely, have them come on יום ראשון. Yom
Rishon.
Right. Okay.
All right. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what Rabbi Meir
says.
אמר לו רבי יהודה,
Amar lo
Rabbi Yehuda,
so Rabbi Yehuda said back to him, אם ברצון חכמים היו עושים
היו כל אדם עושים כן. Im birtzon chachamim hayu osim hayu kol
adam osim kein. If they really did this with the approval of
the sages, so why was it just the אנשי יריחו, Anshei Yericho,
you know, so everybody should be doing it. Whatever it was that
they were doing, presumably he's referring to the קוצרין וגודשין לפני העומר
kotzrin v'godshin lifnei ha-omer of course, as we know in our משנה
Mishna it says you are allowed, but anyway, why didn't everybody do
it? So אלא, ela, so here's Rabbi Yehuda's opinion because he feels
that all of this was sort of antinomian or anomian, you know,
all of this was a variation, so it means that the norm
was not acceptable to do this. So אלו ואלו שלא ברצון חכמים.
eilu v'eilu shelo birtzon chachamim. Since the norm was not to do
this, that's an indication that it was not approved of behavior. None
of it was approved of behavior. Okay, none of it was approved
of, so what's the difference? ושלשה מיחו בידם ושלשה לא מיחו בידם.
u-shlosha michu biyadam v'shlosha lo michu biyadam. So it was not none
of it was approved of, but three they really made a protest
and tried to put a stop to. The other three they tolerated,
but it still was not approved of. So ואלו שלא מיחו בידם,
v'eilu shelo michu biyadam, the following are the things that they did
not protest. מרכיבין דקלים כל היום, markivin d'kalim kol ha-yom, the first
three you mentioned, the the grafting of the palm trees ערב פסח,
Erev Pesach, the כורכין את שמע, korechin et Shma, the wrapping of
the שמע, Shma, וקוצרין וגודשין. v'kotzrin v'godshin. Now we have both mentioned,
we'll go back to that. Both the cutting and the bundling לפני
העומר. lifnei ha-omer. None of that was approved of, but they did
not protest.
Okay. ואלו שמיחו בידם v'eilu shemichu biyadam and the following are things
that they did protest. מתירין גמזיות של הקדש של חרוב ושל שקמה.
matirin gamziyot shel hekdesh shel charuv v'shel shikmah. The fact that they
tried to use the growths of these sycamore trees and carob trees
that
were הקדש. hekdesh. ופורצין פרצות בגנותיהם ופרדסיהם כדי להאכיל לנשורת לעניים בשבתות
ובימים טובים. u-portzin pratzot b'ginoteihem u-fardei-seihem k'dei l'ha'achil l'neshoret l'aniyim b'Shabbatot u-v'yamim
tovim. Okay. And they would right they made the whole they right
they made the holes in order to get have them eat the
fruit, so that they did protest, they tried to put a stop
to. And now he's going to add yet another one. ונותנין פאה
לירק, v'notnin peah l'yarak, they gave פאה peah for from vegetables. Now
you don't give פאה peah from vegetables, but they did. Now what
do we know? What? Just giving the עניים aniyim free food? What
do you care if they give פאה peah for vegetable? Because something
that is פאה peah and מתנות עניים, matnot aniyim, you don't give
תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot from. And if it's not legitimate מתנות עניים,
matnot aniyim, then you're חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u-ma'asrot. So
then the עניים aniyim were eating this without taking תרומות ומעשרות. terumot
u-ma'asrot. And that was the problem. Okay, so he added that extra
one.
So anyway, now what's the גמרא's Gemara problem? Where were we? ומיחו
בידם u-mishu biyadam and they were מוחה. mocheh. Now what was... So
now we understand that's the whole ברייתא. baraisa. Now how's that relevant
to our משנה? Mishna? Because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir did not mention
any discussion of protesting. Only רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda mentioned the issue
of protesting. And he said they did not protest. They didn't protest.
It was all wrong, but they didn't protest. They didn't protest the
harvesting and they didn't protest the bundling. So now גמרא Gemara says
we got a problem. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the one that
talks about protesting or not protesting. So when our משנה Mishna says
they didn't protest, presumably those are the words talking about מיחו michu
are only words that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would talk about. He
was the only one that discussed the issue of מיחו. michu. So
he's the one that's saying they didn't protest. Okay. But our משנה
Mishna says they're allowed to harvest before the עומר, omer, that that
was ברצון חכמים, birtzon chachamim, right? So it doesn't work. Our משנה
Mishna talks about not protesting the גודשים, godshim, that fits with רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because he talks about it was wrong but they
didn't protest it. But it also says they were allowed to cut
before the עומר omer and that doesn't fit with רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that they were not allowed to
cut before the עומר. omer. So how do you make it work?
So the גמרא Gemara says no. The גמרא Gemara says well similar.
ולטעמיך, u-l'tameich, גמרא Gemara says according to you you have this big
קשיא, kashya, this ברייתא baraisa is already a problem or this משנה
Mishna because why? ששה, shisha, how could רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say
six? שבעה הוו, shiva havu, it was seven because רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda added, right he added this thing about the vegetables and the
פאה. peah. So now he's got seven, he doesn't have six. So
we got to do something to fix this ברייתא baraisa anyway. So
I've got the six. אלא סמי מכאן קצירה, ela sami mikan k'tzira,
take out the word קצירה k'tzira from רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would agree that it's totally okay and everybody
could do it, not just אנשי יריחו. Anshei Yericho. Anybody could be
קוצר kotzer in בית השלחין beit ha-shlachin like our משנה Mishna says.
Anybody that's got an irrigated field, געזונטערהייט. gezunterheit. Okay, that's okay. So
the three that were wrong that were not protested included the גודשים,
godshim, and then there were three that were wrong that were protested.
But the קוצרים kotzrim is totally okay. Not wrong, totally okay. So
our משנה Mishna is according to everybody. Our משנה Mishna said, but
that's why our משנה Mishna doesn't just say אנשי יריחו Anshei Yericho
can do it. רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda point is if it really
is רצון חכמים ratzon chachamim then everybody can do it. So our
משנה Mishna says everybody can be קוצר, kotzer, אנשי יריחו Anshei Yericho
was קוצר, kotzer, that's fine. But they were גודשים, godshim, that was
not norm and that was wrong and therefore מיחו michu but לא
מיחו בידם חכמים lo michu biyadam chachamim and that's רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. Okay very nice, now we have clarified that issue about
the about מיחו. michu. So now the other thing is not all
so that was fields that were not field that you brought the
עומר Omer from, but not all harvesting is considered harvesting that would
impinge on the עומר Omer status as ראשית קציר. reishis katzir. If
it's a harvesting for the sake of fodder, that's not a harvesting
and that's not a problem. Okay, so תנן התם, tnan hasam, we
taught over there in a משנה Mishnah in
פאה. Pe'ah. ואלו מפסיקין לפאה. ve'elu mafsikin lepe'ah. So here's פאה Pe'ah
again. The following break up a field for פאה. Pe'ah. The point
of פאה Pe'ah is that you have to give a פאה Pe'ah
for every field, the corner of a field. So you have to
know what's defined as a field. If I've got a huge field
of a thousand acres, that's one field, one פאה. Pe'ah.
But what let's say I've got a river running through it in
the middle, is it one field or two fields? What defines it
then I give two פאות. Pe'as. So what defines it as one
what breaks up the field for the sake of פאה? Pe'ah? הנחל,
hanachal, a נחל nachal which is a river but it also means
a wadi. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi says even if it's not there's no
running water in it but it's a serious riverbed, okay, or maybe
even more, maybe a wadi. השלולית, hashlulit, a שלולית shlulit actually a
running stream. So but the שלולית shlulit as opposed to נחל nachal
we assume that there's actual water running through it. If you have
a נחל nachal you don't need to tell me שלולית shlulit then,
no?
No. A נחל nachal is even if
it's not even if it's dry. And שלולית shlulit is only if
it's running. Right, but even if it's dry but only if
it's the size of a נחל. nachal. No? If something is the
size of a נחל nachal it could be dry. Okay. If something
is a שלולית shlulit smaller, it's
a stream, it's not a river, it's not a wadi but it
has to be running. Okay. ודרך היחיד ודרך הרבים, vederech hayachid vederech
harabim, הרבים, harabim, whether it is a path of an individual or
a or a path of the of the like a like a
public path. דרך הקבוע, derech shekavu'a, right? Right. ושביל, vishvil, correct. So
דרך derech is more like a maybe path and I don't know
what, a street, a private street or a public street. ושביל הרבים
ושביל היחיד vishvil harabim vishvil hayachid or a public path or a
private path. But if it's the path as opposed to a street,
it has to have the following quality. It has to be הקבוע
בימות החמה ובימות הגשמים. hakavu'a bimot hachama ubimot hageshamim. It has to
be a path that that operates even during the rainy season, right?
Some paths get washed out and whatever and you can't use it
during the rainy season. So that would not be significant. It has
to be a path that is fixed and that's used throughout the
year. Not just designated but usable. Okay, right exactly. Okay, so these
things divide the field. והבור, vehabur, בור bur does not mean here
a well. Here means a a field that is unplanted. והניר, vehanir,
a ניר nir is means here field you
have in the middle an unplanted.
Exactly, I have a huge field, in the middle I have a
whole swath, a whole section that I don't plant. Okay, or ניר,
nir, ניר nir is similar, again if I knew agriculture I'd understand
that's not similar at all but I believe that the difference between
ניר nir and בור bur is that ניר nir is a field
that you're letting lay fallow but you plow over, you turn the
you turn the soil. So you're not planting anything that year but
you're turning the soil. בור bur is basically a field that you
just completely ignore. Okay, but either of these things if they were
like a strip in the middle of your field, they separate the
two halves of your field. Okay. וזרע אחר, vezera acher, or if
you've got a different type of a plant in the middle. I've
got wheat here, then I've got corn, then I've got more wheat
over there. So the corn swath in the middle defines that as
separate fields. I'd probably I'd probably have three fields then.
Wheat, corn and wheat then? What?
How do you know when you- whatever if you do it to-
within the context of addressing כלאים, kilayim, if we would learn כלאים
kilayim we would figure out how far you have to plant them
and which things you could plant side by side. But whatever it
is, the fact that you've got some other thing here means that
they're separate fields.
Okay. Okay, וקוצר לשחת vekotzer lishachas and here's the one where why
we were quoting it, or let's say you harvested a section in
the middle for the sake of fodder. So now you've got you
know your wheat there, a blank section here, a harvested section in
the middle and your wheat over there. Now if you were harvesting
for the sake of harvesting, you know making the grain and whatever,
then it wouldn't divide your field then it was just the beginning
of the harvesting. But if you were harvesting for the sake of
fodder, which anyway would take place earlier in the season before the
grain had ripened, so then all of this is here for wheat
and this was harvested in the middle for fodder, not fodder, yes
fodder, anyways that defines it as something different and therefore it splits
the field.
Usually the פאה Pe'ah before the harvest though no?
What? You need to leave the פאה Pe'ah before the harvest. Yes
but not before the harvesting of the fodder which took place at
an earlier stage.
Okay. וקוצר לשחת מפסיק דברי רבי מאיר. vekotzer lishachas mafsik divrei Rabbi
Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim,
but the חכמים chachamim disagree with the שחת shachas case, not with
anything else, just with the שחת shachas case and they say אין
מפסיק אלא אם כן חרש. ein mafsik ela im ken charash. That
in this middle section that you cut for for fodder, that would
not be a מפסיק mafsik unless you plowed it over. You plowed
it over it would sort of become like the ניר. nir. It
would become a field that had been overturned and it would redefine
it as a different field but if you just harvested for the
sake of fodder, that's like a harvesting. So if you're harvesting a
field... Okay, so there you see, so now let's try to connect
this idea with our
משנה. mishnah. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabba
bar bar Chana Amar Rabbi Yochanan רבי מאיר כשיטת רבי שמעון אמרה.
Rabbi Meir k'shitot Rabbi Shimon amra. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir of the
issue of the פאה pe'ah is similar to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
of our משנה. mishnah. Remember רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon of our משנה
mishnah said if you cut for fodder it's not a problem if
you started when it was a third not a third ripe. And
it was only רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that said that even when
it was a third ripe you're cutting for the sake of fodder
that's not a real harvesting. Okay, so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon takes
the more extreme position that anything done for the sake of fodder
not a real harvesting. So the גמרא gemara says רבי מאיר כשיטת
רבי שמעון אמרה. Rabbi Meir k'shitot Rabbi Shimon amra. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir that said that harvesting for fodder separates the field and is
not a harvesting is similar is in the same position of רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דאמר יקצור ויאכיל אף משהביא שליש. D'amar yiktzor viy'achil
af mi-sheheviya shalish. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that you can harvest
the grain before the עומר omer and feed your animal even once
it's a third ripened. אלמא almah obviously הוא קסבר hu kasavar כל
שחת לאו קצירה היא. kol shachas lav k'tzira hi. Anything done even
if it's a third ripened for the sake of fodder is not
a real harvesting and the same it's not a harvesting there it's
also not a harvesting in the field of your you know when
you're thinking about פאה. pe'ah. You don't say oh it's the beginning
of harvesting. No it's a destruction of the strip of the field
and therefore the field is divided. Okay so that's clear. Both of
these things the question is getting it out of the category of
harvesting. By עומר omer to because the עומר omer has to be
your first harvesting so we have to say this is not called
harvesting. And by פאה pe'ah for the strip in the middle to
be significant we have to say it wasn't the beginning of a
process of harvesting. We don't consider what you did to be an
act of harvesting. So the גמרא gemara is saying רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon are essentially saying the same thing
without any qualifications the fact no matter how ripe the grain is
the fact that you're doing it to the sake of fodder means
that it's not an act of harvesting. That's what they're saying. Okay
so now the גמרא gemara says אלמא קסבר כל שחת לאו קצירה
היא. almah kasavar kol shachas lav k'tzira hi. So יתיב רבה yasiv
Rabba so Rabba was sitting וקאמר לה להאי שמעתא v'ka'amar lah l'hai
shemayeta and he was telling over this discussion. So איתיב רבא בר
הונא לרבה aiseiv Rava bar Huna l'Rabba so רבא בר הונא Rava
bar Huna asked him רבה Rabba from the following תוספתא tosefta in
פאה. pe'ah. אכלה חגב achlah chagav let's say here's what's separating your
field. A swath in the middle not you harvested but that nature
harvested for you. Why? Because the חגב chagav the locusts came and
they ate you know a swath in the middle or
כרסמוה נמלים karsimuha nemalim or ants came and they sort of chopped
it down. רש"י Rashi says they attacked from below right and the
locusts attacked right it's natural. So and now you've got a swath
in the middle of your field that's been destroyed by insects an
infestation. Does that separate the two fields for פאה? pe'ah? What's the
הלכה? halacha? Or שבתה הרוח shivasah haruach or the wind destroyed a
section in the middle הכל מודים ha-kol modim everybody agrees that that
by itself does not divide the field. חרש מפסיק לא חרש אינו
מפסיק. charash mafsik lo charash eino mafsik. Only if you then plowed
it over would that divide the field if you did not it
does not divide the field. It's a natural phenomenon and it does
not by itself divide the field. If a whole bunch of trees
like you know fell down and you can't even go from one
side to the other? It's still a חציצה? chatzitza? If it's completely
impassable maybe that's a חציצה. chatzitza. But now we're not talking about
impassable. We're talking about just the fact that you know that might
be like the נחל. nachal. We're not talking about impassable. We're just
talking about the fact that there's not grain growing there right now.
Okay so the גמרא gemara says like this okay so הכל מודים
מאן? ha-kol modim man? Who is being מודה? modeh? Who is shifting
their position? Well it was the position that said before that I
don't need you to plow. Who normally said I don't need you
to plow that's just by cutting down that grain is enough that
was רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir right? So who's the הכל ha-kol that's
מאן? man? רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. That's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who
normally says I don't need you to plow if you're doing it
for fodder but here I do need you to plow. Now I
need to stop and ask you this question. You have these two
phenomena. One is you cut for fodder and the other is insects
destroyed. Which one would you say is more natural is more are
you more inclined to think defines the field as two halves? The
destruction of the insects or the fact that you cut it for
fodder? I'm just curious because the גמרא gemara makes an assumption which
we're not have been my assumption. Insects. You think the insects naturally
defined it as two halves. Okay. Anybody else think it's any differently?
So okay so that's what the גמרא gemara assumes that the insects
is more natural because if you're cutting it maybe we should look
at it as the beginning of a harvest. But I actually thought
the opposite. If you're cutting it it's intentional and if it's intentional
then you're sort of defining it more. If it's an accident if
it's an act of nature it doesn't really redefine you know what
you have as much of as if it's so I would think
that your cutting more defines it as two fields. Anyway the גמרא
gemara assumes like Rishka. The גמרא gemara assumes that if if you're
cutting that's more likely to be considered a harvest and not redefine
it. The insects is more likely to redefine it and therefore we've
got a question. So let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara.
So the גמרא gemara says like this right.
So the גמרא gemara says like this. So it's רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. בשלמא מתניתין אי אמרת בשלמא מתניתין בשלא הביאה שליש. Bishlama
masnis ee amit bishlama
masnis b'shelo heviya shalish.
So now I could say the following. When does רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir say you don't need to overturn and the cutting divides the
field when it is a very objective cutting for fodder, it's not
a סרד. serad. And ברייתא דחרש braisa decharash אין לא חרש לא
in lo charash lo and when do you need to overturn when
the insects destroyed it and you need to plow it over? בשביה
שליש beshivya shelish that it's already a third, so it's much more
likely to consider this part of the field and therefore you need
to overturn it even if the insects destroyed it. אלא אי אמרת
מתניתין Ella i amrat matnisin
you'll see sort of what it's contrasting it to in a minute.
If you say our משנה mishna נמי בשביה שליש nami beshivya shelish
like you're suggesting that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is like רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and our משנה mishna is that you harvest, you cut
it for fodder even when it's a third, so now we've got
a logical problem. What's the problem? הכא דאכלא Hacha de’achla התם קצירה
hasam ketzira אמר רבי מאיר לא שמה קצירה. amar Rabbi Meir lo
shema ketzira. If when it's a third and you cut it, right,
it's not considered a harvesting and that's enough to define it as
two separate fields, הכא לא כל שכן hacha lo kol sheken so
if the animals consume it, that'd certainly define it as two separate
fields. So the גמרא Gemara's assuming like רישא reisha that if the
animals consume it, it more defines it as separate fields than you
harvest. So why does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon why does רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir say that when it's the animals you have to overturn
it? He didn't say that by cutting. The animals should more define
it as separate fields. So with that assumption the גמרא Gemara is
saying it must be that when רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you
don't have to overturn, that's because you cut it for fodder when
it wasn't a third. And therefore it was very objectively for fodder
and therefore you didn't need to to overturn. When the animals destroyed
it and it was already grain and was already a third, that
is not so objective and therefore you do need to overturn to
overturn it. So now we see that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't
hold like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said
according to the way we're reading, only it's only considered a cutting
for fodder when it's not yet a third ripened according to the
way we've just read it. אלא Ella the גמרא Gemara says okay
reverse it. רבי מאיר בשיטת רבי יהודה אמרה. Rabbi Meir beshitas Rabbi
Yehuda amrah. So now you've proven to me that רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir's position of fodder is only when it's less than a third,
so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דאמר
רבי יהודה Deamar Rabbi Yehuda says אימתי eimasai when is it considered
a cutting for fodder and not and not a problem before the
עומר? Omer? בזמן שהתחיל עד שלא הביא שליש Bishman shehishil ad shelo
hevi shelish if you began before it was a third and then
defined really as fodder. אבל אם התחיל משהביא שליש Aval im hishil
mishe’hevi shelish if you began when it was already a third, אסור.
assur. That is forbidden. Okay. So now we have it. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir you proved to me with saying his idea of not
a third, that fits רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. But we're still not
happy. Why not? Just read one more line here. אימור Eimur says
the גמרא דשמעת ליה לרבי יהודה לבהמה. Gemara deshamat lei leRabbi Yehuda
lebehema. Our משנה mishna says you cut it לשחת לבהמה leshachas lebehema
and you feed to your animals. Right. So לאדם מי שמעת
ליה? le’adam mi shamat lei? He didn't say that you eat even
if you cut it for humans. Now what does it mean cutting
it for fodder for humans? So רש"י Rashi says yes, sometimes human
beings can use, you know, this type of fodder that animals would
use, you could use it in certain types of foods. Okay, but
it's not the same as treating it like grain. Okay. So רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir didn't have that qualification. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
if you cut it for fodder, it divides the field. Our משנה
mishna says if you cut it for fodder for animals and then
you feed to your animals, it's very specifically has to be feeding
to your animals. Okay, and he does not say even if you
do it for אדם. adam. דאם כן הוו להו תלתא תנאי De’im
ken havu lehu tlasa tannai because then our משנה mishna would have
three תנאים. tannaim. Our משנה mishna has the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
saying cutting for fodder for animals, then it has
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda saying even only if it's before it's a
שליש, shelish, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon saying even if it's even
if it's a third. So we've been assuming that רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is the same as the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, explicating the
תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. Now if you want to say that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda's statement that less than a third is like רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and would mean even for humans, then he'd be
saying something different than the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. The תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma said only for the בהמה. behema.
And he's not talking about that case.
I understand.
אלא Ella the גמרא Gemara's also who says we have to be
splitting those hairs also. אלא Ella so let's just give the final
answer get out of here. כי אתא רב דימי או רבין Ki
asa Rav Dimi o Ravin when they came from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael אמר amar he said רבי מאיר בשיטת רבי עקיבא רבו אמרה.
Rabbi Meir beshitas Rabbi Akiva rabo amrah. That you're right. Forget רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir connecting him to our משנה. mishna. Our משנה mishna
says either before a third or after a third, but it also
requires for the sake of animals.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that prepared to define it as a cutting
for שחת shachas is not a cutting as it's less than a
third, but doesn't care about animals or humans, that's different than our
משנה mishna because he doesn't care about animals or humans, he cares
that less than a third and that's following רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and and I'll just say and then דהוא אמר dehu amar who
says אף לאדם נמי לא הוי קצירה af le’adam nami lo hevei
ketzira that even if it's for people, if it's less than a
third, it's for שחת shachas and it's not considered to be a
real cutting and we will see this when we pick up.